A Guide to the Records of the American Association of University Women (AAUW), Virginia Tech Chapter, 1926-2008
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Records of the American Association of University Women (AAUW), Virginia Tech Chapter, 1926-2008
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
RG 30/5a
8.7 Cubic Feet; 7 boxes
This collection consists of official records and periodicals from the AAUW, Virginia Tech Chapter and the National AAUW including minutes, administrative records, state and national convention programs, awards and scholarships, publications, and other materials concerning community outreach from 1926-2008.
American Association of University Women. Blacksburg Branch (Va.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated to Special Collections in May 1990. Additions were donated in March 1992 and December 2001.
Administrative History
The American Association of University Women (AAUW) was founded in 1881. The AAUW is a non-profit organization that advocates for the advancement of girls and women through empowerment, research, and advancement. The organization has a nationwide network of 150,000 members, 1,500 branches, and 500 college and university partners. The Virginia Tech chapter was formed in 1926.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of official records and periodicals from both the local AAUW Blacksburg Chapter and the National AAUW including minutes, treasurer's records and administrative materials, membership lists, state and national convention programs, yearbooks, certificates, awards and scholarships, reports, and other materials concerning local and statewide community outreach. Current materials date from the chapter's founding in 1926 through 2008. Series I, folder 17.A contains materials relating to the Mrs. Archie Richmond civil rights controversy.
Arrangement
This collection is organized in seven series.
Series I: Minutes contains meeting minutes from 1930-1992. This series in arranged in reverse chronological order.
Series II: Administrative Documents includes budgets, bylaws, constitutions, treasury and membership reports, foundation and award materials, and organizational histories dating from about 1930-2000. This series is arranged in alphabetical order by material type.
Series III: Activities, Groups, and Community Outreach consists of papers and reports documenting community events, sponsored activities, local and national causes, and support for education equality from 1940-2008. This series is arranged in alphabetical order by folder title.
Series IV: Annual Reports and Publicity Materials contains materials used to create annual reports, annual reports, some correspondence relating to the chapter, information about officers, and some historic clippings from 1937-2007. This series is arranged in alphabetical order by folder title.
Series V: Awards and Community Action includes materials from committees, award ceremonies, scholarships, education events, and non-AAUW conferences from 1926-2002. This series is arranged alphabetically by event type.
Series VI: Periodicals consists of programs and publications from local, state, national, and international conventions and conferences, as well as local chapter scrapbooks, from 1941-1987. This series is arranged geographically, from largest region (International) to smallest region (Blacksburg Chapter).
Series VII: Oversize Materials includes materials relating to the chapter's history and a banner from the 75th anniversary.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; University History; Women -- History
Organizations:
American Association of University Women. Blacksburg Branch (Va.); Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Contents List
- Series I: Minutes, 1930-1992
  - Minutes, 1985-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Minutes, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1964-06-1979-11 (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
  - Minutes, 1945-10-1964-05 (Box 1, Folder 13-17)
  - Documents Relating to the Mrs. Archie Richmond Controversy (Box 1, Folder 17a)
  - Minutes, 1930-12-1945-06 (Box 1, Folder 18-21)
- Series II: Administrative Documents, 1930-2000
  - AAUW Affiliates Agreement (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Committee and Officer Reports (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Administrative Forms and Letters (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Administrative Projects and Study Groups (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Agenda and Board Discussion Materials, 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - AAUW Brance Annual Reports of Interest and Delegates to State Convention (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - AAUW Bylaws (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - AAUW Blacksburg Branch Budget (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - AAUW Blacksburg Branch Bylaws (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Blacksburg Convention, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Blacksburg Branch Name Change Application, 1936 2000 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Branch History (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Branch Presidents List (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Branch Reports, 1960-1974, 1979-1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Constitution and Bylaws, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - AAUW Dues Reports, 1972-1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - AAUW Dues Reports, 1980-1989 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - AAUW Education; Academic Awards (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - AAUW Educational Foundation - Booklets of Named Grants (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - EFP Reports, Materials, and Publicity (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "In Lieu of Old Yearbooks" (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - AAUW Legislative Committee (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Loan Fund Administration (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Legislative Letters: A Representative Sample of Branch Involvement (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Regional History of AAUW Chapters (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - AAUW Blacksburg Branch Interest Survey Sheets (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - AAUW Blacksburg Branch Surveys (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Tax Exemptions and Liability INS (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Treasurer's Report, Membership Report, and Calendar (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Blacksburg Branch Treasurer's Reports, 1930-1950 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - AAUW Treasurer's Record Books, 1938-1940, 1962-1972 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Blacksburg Treasurer's Reports, 1977-1988 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - AAUW Treasurers Record Books, 1972-1980, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1982-1997 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Treasurer's Official Membership Lists (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Series III: Activities, Groups, and Community Outreach, 1940-2008
  - "All Roads Lead to Richmond" AAUW Convention, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - AAUW Activities, 1940-1949 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - AAUW Activities, 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - AAUW Activities, 1970-1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - AAUW Activities, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Copies of Letters and Clippings, AAUW, 1930-1940 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Cultural Interests (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Designing and Implementing a Successful Educational Equity Conference", 1998-01 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Drunk Driving Awareness Group (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - AAUW Annual Booksale: Reports, Publicity, and Advertising (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Education, 1943-1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Educational Equity Committee, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - AAUW Blacksburg Branch: Equal Rights Amendment (Box 3, Folder 13-15)
  - Fourth Annual Educational Equity Conference "Growing Smart in Science, Math, and Technology - What's Working for Girls in School", 1996-01 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - AAUW History Group (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Activities for AAUW IMP Council, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Insight: New Visions and Expanded Horizons," AAUW Annual Convention, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "Your Legal Rights as a Woman: A Handbook for Virginians" (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1983-1988 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "Promoting Professional Development," 1987 AAUW Seminar, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - AAUW Legal Advocacy Fund (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Literature Group Materials (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Peace Child (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Peace and National Security (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - AAUW Reading Lists: Summer, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - AAUW Resolutions (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Seventh Annual Conference on Educational Equality: "Gender Gaps: Success and Failure" (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Sixth Annual Equity Conference (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - State Convention Blacksburg, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - AAUW Sponsored Events and Projects (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Third Annual Educational Equity Converence, 1995-01 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - "The Third Shift- Women Learning Online" (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Women in Poverty (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Yearbook (Copy), 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - 21st Century AAUW Branch Recognition Program Blacksburg, Virginia, 2002-2008 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - 21st Century Branch Recognition Program Blacksburg, Virginia, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Series IV: Annual Reports and Publicity Materials, 1939-2007
  - AAUW Documents, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - AAUW Documents, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - AAUW Documents, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - AAUW Documents, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - AAUW Documents, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - AAUW Documents, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - AAUW Documents, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - AAUW Documents, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - AAUW Documents, 1988-1993 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - AAUW Documents, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - AAUW Documents, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - AAUW Documents, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - AAUW Documents, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - AAUW Documents, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - AAUW Documents, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - AAUW Documents, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - AAUW Documents, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - AAUW Documents, 2000-2001 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - AAUW Documents, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - AAUW Documents, 2002-2003 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - AAUW Documents, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - AAUW Documents, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - AAUW Documents, 2006-2007 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - AAUW Documents, 2006-2007 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - AAUW Blacksburg Branch Disbands, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - AAUW Corporate Representative (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - AAUW Legal Advocacy Fund, Progress in Equity Award 1997-1998, The Women's Center at Virginia Tech, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - AAUW Publicity, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - AAUW of Virginia Branch Recognition, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Blacksburg Officers, 1964-1990 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Connie Anderson Correspondence, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - International Relations, 1981-1987 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Kathryn Brennan Book Materials, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Marion Wooldridge Memorial (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Neighborhood Groups, 1984-1997 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Press Releases and Relevant Information, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Program Activities, 1983-1988 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Publicity Clippings, 1939-1951 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Publicity Clippings, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Series V: Awards and Community Action,, 1926-2002, undated
  - AAUW Awards Newsletters, 1982-1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Certificates and Awards (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Community Action Awards, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - AAUW Educational Foundation Award (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Educator of the Year Award (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - AAUW E.E. Committee, 1998-2000 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Fifth Annual Educational Equity Conference - "Girls in the Middle: Working to Succeed in School" (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Gender Equity in Science" (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "Great Decisions 2004" 50th Anniversary Edition (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Leadership Award - Fundraising, 1984-2006 (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
  - AAUW Middle School Book Project (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Re-entry Scholarship (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Science Fair (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - AAUW School Recognition Program, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - YMCA Women's Leadership Awards (Box 5, Folder 16-17)
  - AAUW 75th Anniversary Luncheon, Donaldson Brown Hotel, Virginia Tech (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - AAUW Photo Album, 1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - AAUW Historic Highlights, 1926-2001 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - AAUW Annual Spring Luncheon, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - AAUW Historic Highlights, 1926-2001 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Series VI: Periodicals, 1941-1987
  - IFUW Conference, Vancouver, Canada "The Dignity and Worth of the Human Person", 1980 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - IFUW Nineteenth Annual Conference, Directory of Enrolled Members, Stirling, Scotland, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - IFUW Report of the Nineteenth Conference, Grenoble, France, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - IFUW Report on the Twentieth Conference, Vancouver, Canada, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - IFUW Report of the Twentieth Conference, Vancouver, Canada, French edition, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - AAUW 1981 National Biannual Convention, Boston, Massachusetts (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - AAUW 1981 National Biannual Convention, Washington, D.C. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - AAUW 1951 National Convention, Atlantic City, New Jersey (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - AAUW 1961 National Convention, Washington D.C. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - AAUW 1977 National Convention, Minneapolis, Minnesota (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - AAUW 1979 National Convention, Albuquerque, New Mexico (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Foundation Night - Awards and Grants, Albuquerque, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - AAUW 1948 State Convention, Norfolk, Virginia (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - AAUW 1949 State Convention, Alexandria, Virginia (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - AAUW 1963 State Convention, Abingdon, Virginia (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - AAUW 1967 State Convention, Natural Bridge, Virginia (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - AAUW 1971 State Convention, Fredericksburg, Virginia (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - AAUW Virginia Division Banquet Program, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - AAUW Blacksburg Branch Annual Meeting Programs, 1941, 1946-1987 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, AAUW Blacksburg, 1964-1972 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook, AAUW Blacksburg, 1950-1957 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook, AAUW Blacksburg, 1975-1979 (Box 6)
- Series VII: Oversize Materials
  - AAUW Blacksburg Clubs and Organizations (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - AAUW Blacksburg Chapter 75th Anniversary Celebration Banner (Box 7, Folder 2)